Jacob Kaplan, PhD

Email: jk7785@princeton.edu

Websites: jacobdkaplan.com & crimedatatool.com

GitHub: github.com/jacobkap

Professional Profile

Data Scientist with a Ph.D. in Criminology, possessing extensive experience in managing and analyzing large, complex data. I am an expert in data cleaning, analysis, and visualization, and have developed user-friendly tools, such as the Crime Data Tool, and built several R packages, demonstrating my ability to make data analysis accessible to various audiences. My academic portfolio includes 14 peer-reviewed publications and a textbook that introduces the programming language R. My unique blend of technical expertise, research acumen, and communication skills underscores my commitment to transforming complex data into valuable insights.

Education

| PhD in Criminology | University of Pennsylvania | 2016-2020 |
|------------------------|---|-----------|
| MS in Criminology | University of Pennsylvania | 2015-2016 |
| BS in Criminal Justice | California State University, Sacramento | 2011-2015 |

Technical Skills: R (10+ years), Git, JavaScript, Stata, LaTeX

Experience

Professional Specialist Princeton University

2021-Present

- Developing a toolkit to measure racial bias in law enforcement among traffic stops.
- Designed, tested, and deployed automated workflows for categorizing and clustering thousands of unique strings using large language models.
- Collaborated on a cross-disciplinary project comparing sociodemographic and political attributes of police to civilians in corresponding jurisdictions.
- Managed and cleaned data from 99 police agencies, performing probabilistic matching against a massive-scale (200+ million rows) voting database.
- Conducted code reviews for team members to ensure coding accuracy and adherence to style guidelines.

Committee Member Federal Bureau of Investigation –

Uniform Crime Reporting Subcommittee

2022

- Served as one of 17 voting members, providing subject matter expertise to inform policy.
- Reviewed, advised, and voted on potential changes to the FBI's crime data collection, focusing on a balance between the usefulness of the data and the burden on agencies to generate it.

Postdoctoral Fellow University of Pennsylvania

2020-2021

- Embedded researcher at the Philadelphia District Attorney's Office, analyzing the life cycle of gun cases from arrest to final disposition.
- Spearheaded a privacy-focused project determining optimal anonymity levels for safely releasing datasets containing Personal Identifiable Information (PII).

Selected Data Science Projects

Crime Data Tool | crimedatatool.com

- Built an interactive platform enabling non-programmers to access government crime data.
- Simplified data processing workflows and provided customizable visualizations and downloadable data for users.
- Developed the tool using JavaScript and HTML, with data processing in R.

Uniform Crime Reporting (UCR) Program Data | Harvard Dataverse

- Cleaned, standardized, and published FBI UCR data as R and Stata files, making the dataset accessible to researchers worldwide.
- Has over 250 citations in peer-reviewed journal articles.
- Standardizes column names and values, resolved data errors, and accounts for naming convention changes over time.

fastDummies | CRAN (2.1 million downloads)

• Developed an R package for quick and efficient creation of binary columns from categorical columns, and dummy rows based on all combinations of categorical and date columns.

Selected Publications

A Criminologist's Guide to R: Crime by the Numbers | Chapman & Hall/CRC The R Series

- Authored an introductory textbook on the R programming language, combining crime data examples with practical programming techniques.
- Covers data gathering, cleaning, visualization (through graphs and maps), project management, and introduces the concept of *mise en place* in the context of project planning.
- Includes lessons on ggplot2, dplyr, tidyr, readr, stringr, regular expressions through grep and gsub, sf, leaflet, rvest, pdftools, and tidygeocoder.

Ba, B., Ge, H., **Kaplan, J.**, Knox, D, Komisarchik, M., Lanzalotto, G., Mariman, R., Mummolo, J., Rivera, R., & Torres, M. "**Political diversity in U.S. police agencies."** (Accepted at *American Journal of Political Science.*)

- Compared whether police officers in 99 of the largest 100 agencies are similar to civilians in their jurisdiction in terms of demographics, socioeconomic factors, and political affiliation.
- Compared officer behavior on these traits in Houston and Chicago to measure if they behave differently.

Block, K., & Kaplan, J. (2022). An analysis of National Hockey League playoff games and city level crime counts. *Crime & Delinquency*. https://doi.org/10.1177/00111287221118879

- Analyzed crime data from 15 cities to study whether crime changed when an NHL playoff game occurred at home compared to away.
- Found that home games are associated with 7% more disorder and 4% more property crimes.
- Selected coverage: New York Times